<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The evill spirit conjur'd, and cast out of the Parliament</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84179</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3555B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R225958</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895652</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895652</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153201</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84179)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153201)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2354:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The evill spirit conjur'd, and cast out of the Parliament</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14, [8], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for R.F. and are to be sold by St. Dunstans Church,  and in the upper ile of the New-Exhange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A 2A B C⁴ (-2A1).</note>
                  <note>Caption title on 2A2r: To the supreme authority of this commmonwealth of England, the honourable court of Parliament now sitting ... .</note>
                  <note>Caption title on 2A6r: Animadversions on the petition.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Expulsion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153201:1"/>
            <p>THE Evill Spirit Conjur'd, AND Caſt out of the PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>R. F.</hi> and are to be ſold by St. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church, and in the upper Ile of the New-Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, 1653.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:153201:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153201:2"/>
            <head>THE Evill Spirit Conjur'd, And caſt out of the PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <p>A Melancholly miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous ſpirit having crept of late into the <hi>Parliament,</hi> under I know not what pretext of <hi>Godlineſs</hi> (as the <hi>Devil</hi> is never more <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> than when he transforms himſelf into an <hi>angel</hi> of <hi>light</hi>)
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:153201:3"/>in the perſons of ſome who craftily had counterfeited themſelves good <hi>Patriots,</hi> and zealous for the <hi>Religion, Laws,</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> of the Land, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til finding themſelves in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, they preſently caſt off their mask, and declared the ſpirit which was in them, playing ſuch reaks there, as never did any pernicious ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in houſe which was hanted and poſſeſs'd before. The <hi>Lord General</hi> and others prudently perceiving it (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes carefully vigilant for the Common good) and fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding how much they had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed their truſt and ſuffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153201:3"/>in Electing them, timely provided to caſt this ſpirit forth, before its exorbitancy ſhould proceed ſo far, and arrive to ſuch a heighth, as to diſturb the peace of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, and quite ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the intended ſettlement, and eſtabliſhment thereof; yet this not without firſt proceeding with ſuch matu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in doing it (to diſabuſe ſuch, who ignorantly elſe perhaps might have imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that in lieu of a bad ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, they had caſt out a good) as they expected with much longanimity, until it ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently had declar'd it ſelf in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153201:4"/>divers Actions, tending to the ſubverſion of the <hi>Religion,</hi> &amp; <hi>Laws,</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> of the free-born people of <hi>England,</hi> which they were conſtituted there to eſtabliſh and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, as by the ſeditious Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chings of thoſe of their facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in <hi>Black-Friers &amp;c.</hi> ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently appear'd, they uttering more ſcandalous and ſcurril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous things in the <hi>Pulpit</hi> there, than ever did the <hi>Play-houſe,</hi> againſt which they preacht ſo much.</p>
            <p>Which action of his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency and others was recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with ſo general applauſe and ſatisfaction of all, as the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153201:4"/>Bels were rung for joy, and the ſmiles outwardly appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring on every face, did ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently declare the inward <hi>Iubilee</hi> of their hearts; The twelfth of <hi>December</hi> being render'd as Celebrous by it, and worthy to be ever cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated with Bels, Bonfires, and Thankſgiving, as was the fifth of <hi>November</hi> for the happy deliverance of the <hi>Parliament</hi> before. For what true born <hi>Engliſhman</hi> would not rejoice, who loved his Country, and the honour of his Nation, to ſee that ſpirit caſt out of the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> that had been ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153201:5"/>(had it been longer tolerated) it would not have left the leaſt footſteps or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morials of its Antient Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Lawes and Liberties? and had done actions ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly ſhamefull and inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious (to the Grief of the other Members of the Houſe who more prudent and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious, were joined with them, and forcibly hurryed away by the impetuous tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of thoſe who were agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated by this ſpirit) as would have call'd an Infamy upon our Nation, not only from the remoteſt parts of the VVorld, but even from the <hi>Barbarians</hi> themſelves,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153201:5"/>who for all their <hi>barbariſm</hi> were never ſo unjuſt as they.</p>
            <p>Who would not rejoice to have that ſpirit diſautho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized, which was ſo unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy its authority, as whileſt the grave Reaſonings, and prudent Diſcourſes of other <hi>Parliaments</hi> were the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of all neighbouring Nations, this ſpirit, as if it were beſotted with its place, (which ordinarily renders others wiſer,) to the indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of all the wiſer ſort, would riſe up with its Hat at its fingers ends, (like a School-boy ſaying Grace) and inſtead of all other Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153201:6"/>and Diſcourſe ſay for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth, <hi>That notwithſtanding all that could be ſaid, his ſpirit told him it was ſo, and ſo.</hi> And if this was not declining to the ſpirit of Tyranny, let any one be Judge, when <hi>Stat pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ratione voluntas, my Reaſon is my Will,</hi> is the higheſt point of Tyranny as can be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned?</p>
            <p>Who finally would not rejoyce to have that ſpirit caſt out, and ſilenced, who would have ſilenc'd all but it ſelf? and ſhortly Enacted, that it ſhould be a crime for any one to laugh, or be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, under the pretence of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153201:6"/>Godlineſs (forſooth) only to render Religion irkſome, odious, and burthenſom un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all, which being of it ſelf a chearfull thing, as the holy Scripture teſtifies, <hi>Hilarem datorem diligit Deus, &amp;c.</hi> that <hi>God loves the chearfull Giver,</hi> they on the contrary would make it ſo ſullen and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly a thing, as our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, alwayes of a gay and jovial diſpoſition, would never brook nor endure it. Religion being not to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and adminiſtred unto us, as a Medicin, with loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing and bitterneſs, but as our meat, and daily food,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153201:7"/>ſavoury and pleaſant to the taſt, to delight the palat, and provoke the appetite.</p>
            <p>For the farther diſcovery of this ſpirits miſchievous diſpoſition, and pernicious machinations and deſignes, I remit the Reader to theſe following Animadverſions, written ſome moneths be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore its caſting out of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, as a preſage of what ſhould afterwards enſue; where, though then I ſtruck at them thorough others ſides, I being alwayes moſt cautious not to offend thoſe in authority, being alſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed that <hi>furor eſt ſcribe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153201:7"/>contraeos, qui praeſcribere poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt,</hi> yet now I dare confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently draw the Curtain which ſhadowed it before, and invite them to the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it themſelves, with this avow, <hi>de te Fabula nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur,</hi> that it was meant by them, whoſe cuſtom it was, for the deceiving of the people, to ſuborn ſome of their own Faction to Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion them to do that, which they were reſolved to doe before.</p>
            <p>Mean time let us congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulate with his Excellency and the reſt, and ſing Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negyriques in his praiſe for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153201:8"/>this great Action, and (if I may ſay it) greater than all his other Victories; the other being only over men, but this over the infernal ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; the other not being without bloodſhed, and making of Widdows and Fatherleſſe, but this preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving us from it, and the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities of a new Warre, which this fiery ſpirit would have driven us unto, might he have been let go on.</p>
            <p>And if any demand, what we ſhould doe with him, now he is caſt out of the <hi>Parliament?</hi> by my Advice, as thoſe <hi>Devils</hi> who were
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153201:8"/>caſt out by our <hi>Saviour,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Swine which they poſſeſſed afterwards, were all precipitated into the Sea, ſo I could wiſh they might be all ſhipt, and ſent away by Sea from the <hi>Old,</hi> to <hi>New England,</hi> as a juſt pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for their attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to have made a <hi>New England</hi> of the <hi>Old.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However ſince ſuch ſpirits as theſe are not only caſt out by Prayer and Faſting, but ſomtimes by force and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence (as <hi>Cor. Agripp.</hi> teſtifies) let us not only pray, but uſe our utmoſt endeavors, as we have done for the expelling
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153201:9"/>him, that this ſpirit ſerve us not, as that wicked one did in the Goſpel, who being caſt out, and the houſe clean ſwept of him, did but wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der about a while, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards returned ſeven times more wicked then he was before; but of this we need take no care, things are in good hands, and we may no wayes doubt, but thoſe who have ſo well begun, will not be wanting to the perfectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of them.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:153201:9"/>
            <head>To the Supreme Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of <hi>England,</hi> The Honourable Court of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament now ſitting,</head>
            <head type="sub">The humble Petition of ſeveral of the Godly party in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Salop,</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>Sheweth.</opener>
            <p>THat we cannot omit the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of all thoſe various Providences God hath made his people in this Nation partakers of, in owning our Armies, and making them both formidable to, and victorious over, our Enemies at Sea and Land; in ſtaining the glory of the proud, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>degrading unprofitable men from
<pb facs="tcp:153201:10"/>their ſtations, and planting you in their room, whoſe beginnings begin to revive our hopes, That our Lord Ieſus Chriſt will yet have in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> men executing judgement, and ſpeaking the truth. Certainly if you go on, we doubt not but the children that are to be born will have cauſe to call you bleſſed, as the repairers of our Breaches, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorers of paths to dwel in, and you will render your ſelves of more worth and value than thouſands, ſo that your precedency of Honour and Grace, will tranſcend your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors; and in all probability, God will eſtabliſh you as ſo many Luminaries in your ſtations, to ſhine more and more unto the day of our deliverance. In hopes whereof, as alſo of your real inclinations to hearken to the deſires of the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Saint, and of thoſe that wiſh well to Truth &amp; Peace, amongſt the other large endeavours of others, we have taken the liberty of preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſmall mite of our Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals (which we hope will be looked
<pb facs="tcp:153201:10"/>at) amongſt the thouſand of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That as God hath truſted you in a ſpecial manner with the guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Truth and Goſpel, you will have a ſpecial eye to the propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation thereof. And becauſe there ar many idle, ignorant, ſcandalous, &amp; malignant Miniſters permitted, that endeavour the ſubverſion thereof, as apears to many of the dear Saints of Chriſt, to the great grief of their ſpirits; We humbly deſire that ſome ſpeedy courſe may be taken for the ejection of ſuch men, and the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of thoſe that are fit and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for ſo great a work; and that thoſe may not be ſuffered as Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers thereof, who hate to ſee it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper, and ſtand like the Red Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon ready to devour the child Grace as ſoon as born.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That notwithſtanding the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of many of the People, and the great deliverances vouchſafed them, yet they ſcarcely know them, as by the effects of them, in any encouragement they have yet received, more than the moſt noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb facs="tcp:153201:11"/>and bittereſt of your Enemies: It is propoſed, that you will have a ſpecial regard to your friends above your enemies. Had the late King prevailed, his friends had received large rewards, as appears by his own Ingagements, you and yours threatned with total deſtruction: Oh then why ſhould you not coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance your friends as well as your enemies theirs? we hope you will not tread in the paths of your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors to reward evil for good; but will give the right child to the right mother, and ſuffer thoſe now to rejoyce with you, who have former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mourned with you, and will ſtill (while you are for God) live and die with you.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Becauſe we hear many Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers complain, who have ventured their lives from the beginning, and want imployment ſince their willing ſubmiſſion to former commands of Disbanding; we humbly propoſe, That a deep inſpection may be made in your Army, for the ejection of thoſe that would not be liſted for
<pb facs="tcp:153201:11"/>you ſo long as they could find an Army with which to fight againſt you, and the number may be made up again by thoſe who have been your conſtant friends.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That whereas many men by their fawning flatteries lie at your doors out of ſiniſter ends, to beg for places, we deſire that none may be admitted to any place of truſt, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Army or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, but ſuch as are known to you for men of fidelity and integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or elſe commended to you by the Certificate of five or ſix of your Friends, that ſo things may be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on more by the publick ſpirit of the Saints, than the private ſpirit of any whatſoever.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That whereas we hear many of our Nation ſaying to you, as the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> take away our burthens, take away our taxations; we further propoſe, That the burthen of Contribution may be laid upon thoſe who have been the grand Incendiaries and Contrivers of the War (we mean the Cavaliers)
<pb facs="tcp:153201:12"/>it being unjuſt (as we humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that they ſhould cut out the work, and we bear the burthen, they double the tale of Brick, and we do the Task: O let the right child have the right Mother, it will make them more willing to ſit ſtill,</p>
            <p n="6">6. That whereas many take liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of keeping Wakes, ſetting up Morice Dances, and other prophane Sports, againſt which there is no particular Law; we humbly deſire ſome poſitive Rules may be framed for ſuppreſſing thereof.</p>
            <p n="7">7. In regard it it generally ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, that the foul Sins of Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery and Fornication are too fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently unpuniſhed, more than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the day of our deliverance, for which our Enemies reproach us, ſich the Act only limits the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the teſtimony of two Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes; that a mock may not be made of ſuch foul ſins, We deſire a way may be found, and ſome ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Law inſtituted for the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met thereof.</p>
            <p n="8">8. That in regard of the freedom
<pb facs="tcp:153201:12"/>given to Saints in their ſeveral Churches and meetings on the Lords day, is abuſed, ſo that Papiſts and other prophane perſons take liberty of contemning the Sabbath, and publick Ordinances, and ſpend the day vainly and idly in their houſes, or elſe walking in the Fields; we propoſe, That ſome ſpecial courſe may be taken of reſtraint, that the freedom of the Saints may not be turned to the prophanation of the Lords Day.</p>
            <p n="9">9. That the Excize may be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in the oppreſſive manner of far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it, that poor people may not be bought and ſold in this Nation, as too frequently they are, and ſome raiſe vaſt eſtates by the bargain.</p>
            <p n="10">10. That the poor which dayly ſwarm in <hi>England,</hi> both in City and Country, begging in the Highways, and at our houſes, to the great dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour and prejudice of the Nation, may in ſome due way be provided for, and not ſuffered to wander as Vagabonds upon the face of the earth.</p>
            <closer>And your Petitioners ſhall pray, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="response_to_petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:153201:13"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153201:13"/>
            <head>Animadverſions ON THE PETITION.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is nothing more ſpecious than the name of <hi>Reformation,</hi> and nothing leſs, than the thing it ſelf (I mean that which the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar magnifie, and cry up ſo much) the diſeaſe of mens minds, rather than of the Times, untill their <hi>Imagination</hi> fools them into a real malady, and never lets them recover
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:153201:14"/>afterwards; the Itch of Good Times, and the Ulcer of Ill; moſt pernicious to Kingdoms and Commonwealths, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes Enemy to preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: Every one who would trouble the State, taking it for their pretext, till getting into higheſt place, and looking on things at neerer diſtance, they ſee the Impoſſibility of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming them; when caſting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all care and hope of it, the next take up that pretext which they have quitted, and with as great privat heat, and as little for the publique good, never leave putting for it, till they have obtain'd the others place; whence it conſequently follows, that but open this Gate once of Reformation (which their ſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and juſtling never ſuffers to cloſe again) and you Introduce by it, nothing but diſorder and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153201:14"/>confuſion. I grant you yet, it hath done great things in the World, but undone greater; and ſome good, but far more harm and miſchief; theſe bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie Reformers ſeeing ſomewhat or other which they would a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, but not a hundred others which they marr in mending it; whence the Wiſe, when they ſee things amiſſe, meaſure their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſes by the poſſibility, and utility of amending them, which when they find wanting, they pity the Condition of poor <hi>Humanity,</hi> that hath nothing ſo abſolutely good, as to be whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exempt from <hi>fault</hi> and <hi>blame,</hi> rather than vex and torment her for it, by <hi>tampering</hi> ſo long to mend it, till they marr it quite. Of which over-buſie ſo long to mend it, till they marr it quite. Of which over-buſie <hi>folly</hi> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation in particular are Tax'd; it having paſt almoſt into Proverb, That your <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh-man</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:153201:15"/>never knows when things are well.</p>
            <p>And ſuch <hi>Reformers</hi> as theſe they were, who lately repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this Petition unto the <hi>Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> Houſe of <hi>Parliament,</hi> under the name of the County of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lop,</hi> though their reſtriction to <hi>ſeveral of the</hi> Godly party there, ſufficiently acquits the County, and declares them to he ſuch as one pleaſantly deſcribes,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A ſort of hot-headed, half-witted Fellows, who in the vehemency of their zeal have more harm'd and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiev'd</hi> Chriſtian Religion, <hi>than</hi> Turk, Jew, <hi>or</hi> Infidel <hi>ever did, and have more texts of Scripture for it too, than the other out of the</hi> Talmude, <hi>or</hi> Alcoran; <hi>who have found out a new way under the name of the</hi> Lord, <hi>to aboliſh the memory of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>and of that of</hi> God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, <hi>all Chriſtianity; being the worſt ſort of Affectation, affecting
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153201:15"/>nothing but what is contrary and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe to all good manners, and edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Who are more familiar with the</hi> Lord, <hi>than to ſtand upon</hi> Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies <hi>with him, and approach him with far leſſe</hi> Reverence <hi>than a</hi> Serving-man <hi>does his</hi> Maſter, <hi>or a</hi> Clown <hi>his</hi> Landlord: <hi>ſo hating the name of</hi> Gentleman, <hi>as they cann't indure</hi> God <hi>ſhould be ſerv'd like one, and ſo abhorring the name of</hi> Church <hi>as they wage war with the very ſtones of it</hi> (<hi>like</hi> cowardly Currs, <hi>who bite the ſtones, when they cannot harm the perſons</hi>) <hi>confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by it all things, ſacred, and profane: Mean time, any place ſerves them to Preach in, as any place, indeed, is good enough for their Preaching, who teach nothing bu</hi> Sedition, <hi>and</hi> Infatuation: <hi>ſo as whilſt others people</hi> Heaven <hi>with their Preaching, theſe people</hi> Bed-I am. <hi>Mean while they wave the</hi> Evangeliſts, <hi>and flie to the explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153201:16"/>of the</hi> Prophets, <hi>the better to hide their Ignorance, (ſince ther all are almoſt Ignorant alike) like him, who when he could not</hi> run, <hi>challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged an excellent</hi> Footman <hi>to</hi> flie <hi>with him. Men indulgent only to their own Vices, but moſt rigid to thoſe of other men; who call themſelves</hi> pure, <hi>like him, who being all over defiled, bragg'd, He had never a ſpot on him; and thanking</hi> God, <hi>with the</hi> Phariſee, <hi>for not being like other men: it being the trueſt word they ever ſaid in their lives; for they are worſe than they.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now let us ſee whether this Character fits not our Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners, as well as if it had been made for them, by conferring their <hi>Petitions</hi> with theſe <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madverſions</hi> of ours.</p>
            <p>And firſt, to ſay nothing of their <hi>Preface,</hi> nor their Goodly <hi>ſtile,</hi> all <hi>ſtuff'd</hi> and <hi>interlarded</hi> with <hi>Scripture</hi> phraſe, ſo ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153201:16"/>alleg'd, as I will not ſay their reading of the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſeems to make them mad, but certainly this I dare affirm, that thoſe who read it leſſe, write far better, and more ſenſe than they, and would never have ſaid the <hi>paths to dwell in,</hi> (as they do) but rather the <hi>paths to walk in,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the more proper <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphore;</hi> ſo abuſing every where the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſtile, as <hi>Piſtols</hi> phraſe in the play, <hi>He hears with ears,</hi> would no more ſeem to <hi>Sir Hugh</hi> ſuperfluous, and abſurd: But they are <hi>thoſe dear Saints of Jeſus Chriſt</hi> (as they ſpeak of) and therefore have the liberty of profaning the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture on every occaſion; but for their <hi>ſanctity,</hi> believe it who liſts for me, for my part, I believe none to be leſſe <hi>Saints,</hi> than thoſe who call themſelves ſo the moſt; and give me the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153201:17"/>
               <hi>dead,</hi> and take the <hi>living</hi> he that will: ſo it ſhall alwayes be in my <hi>Letanie,</hi> to deliver me from the <hi>Devil</hi> in an <hi>Angels</hi> ſhape, and I'll deliver my ſelf from the <hi>Devil</hi> in his own ſhape well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough.</p>
            <p>But let us come to their Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and in the firſt four we ſhall obſerve a vehement deſire they have, That none but they ſhould be admitted to the charge of the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> of the Command of the <hi>Army,</hi> of the Government of the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,</hi> and finally, to the diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution of all other Preferments and Rewards; they ſeeming much troubled that they are not conferr'd upon them: and troubled ſtill may they be, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than we ſhould ever be troubled with them. By which, we may perceive them to be ſome diſcarded party, caſheer'd
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153201:17"/>from the Army for their cowar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, and want of diſcipline; ſome rejected, and excluded from the Government of the Commonwealth, for their want of <hi>Talent,</hi> and <hi>non-ſufficiency;</hi> and finally, ſome refuſe ſtuff, and out-caſts of the Miniſtry, for their <hi>turbulency,</hi> and <hi>non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity;</hi> people of no parts, nor merit at all; elſe 'twere to tax the <hi>State,</hi> and the wiſdom, and prudent Conduct of the <hi>General</hi> and <hi>Officers,</hi> for not admitting them to Charge and Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Such <hi>raſh</hi> and <hi>ſtupid</hi> fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, and ſuch <hi>Poltrons</hi> and <hi>Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> withall, as, ſhould I <hi>give the right child to the right mother,</hi> which they urge more than once, I could ſhew how they never yet had the management of affairs, but that they brought them to ruine &amp; <hi>deſtruction;</hi> nor ever fought, but either they
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153201:18"/>were <hi>beaten,</hi> or <hi>ran-away;</hi> which being ſo, far be it from the Commonwealth to have ſuch to reform and govern it, who are hardly fit to govern a Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers, or a Botchers ſhop; and far be the <hi>Omen</hi> from our <hi>ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victorious</hi> and <hi>conquering Army,</hi> to have ſuch as theſe mens For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes joyn'd with theirs, or to be mix'd with thoſe, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve not to be named the ſame day a brave ſpirit, and valiant man is mentioned: No, <hi>live</hi> the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> and <hi>flouriſh</hi> the <hi>Army</hi> ſtill, and it ſhall never ſhame nor repent us of our change of Government, ſo long as ſuch as theſe come not to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern it, Men of ſo narrow, &amp; ſo Ignoble minds, as nothing great and generous ever entred into their breſts; for ſo 'twould be a degree below ſervitude, nothing making ſervitude more intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153201:18"/>than the Ignobility of the Maſter; and thoſe who can ſuffer ſuch as theſe to command over them, deſerve worſe. And for the Government of the Church, we had done nothing, (or rather too much) to have ſhaken off the yoak of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Lambeth,</hi> to ſubmit our necks at laſt to the <hi>Kirk</hi> Government of a ſort of <hi>Banbury-men,</hi> of <hi>John of Leydens</hi> and <hi>Knipperdollings,</hi> who would govern us juſt as they did the Town of <hi>Munſter,</hi> till with their fine ſpirit, and Revelations, they had brought all to confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and deſtruction, as they did there, and tyrannize over us a hundred times worſe than the others did: who, ſince they urge their merit, (leſt we ſhould ſeem to grant them nothing) let us accord them this, that they were the firſt Authors of the change of Government, tis true,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153201:19"/>but not of <hi>this,</hi> nor <hi>that,</hi> they being ever Enemies of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Government, and as they were formerly of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> ſo will they be now of the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth,</hi> unleſſe they may have the <hi>Government</hi> of it themſelves, as they ſufficiently declare by that exception, and clauſe of theirs, (in the end of their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond petition) That <hi>whilſt they are for God,</hi> (that is, <hi>for them,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their own Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation) they <hi>will live and dye with them,</hi> (and not otherwiſe;) a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtriction, which had it iſſued from the pen of any <hi>Papiſt,</hi> or <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> they had been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently exclaim'd againſt, for <hi>Malignants, Seditious,</hi> and Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to the Commonwealth: but theſe men <hi>are the dear Saints of Chriſt,</hi> and may ſay and do any thing.</p>
            <p>To conclude then with them,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153201:19"/>before we paſs to their other <hi>Petitions,</hi> we may anſwer them in urging of their merits, as <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon</hi> did a certain treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Commander of a place, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching his beholdingneſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him for delivering of it up, <hi>That if he had not betray'd it, he had not ſo ſoon been maſter of it;</hi> 'tis true, but that made him rather <hi>fear,</hi> than <hi>reward</hi> him for his <hi>Treachery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To proceed then, after, in the end of their 4th Petition, they inſinuate their deſire. That <hi>none ſhould be advanc'd to any place of Truſt,</hi> either <hi>in the Army,</hi> or <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth,</hi> but ſuch <hi>as ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended by the Certificat of ſome five or ſix of them,</hi> that ſo <hi>things</hi> (as they ſay) <hi>may be carryed on more by the publique ſpirit of the Saints, than the privat ſpirit of any whatſoever;</hi> (bold words, and glancing at thoſe in Authority, and in dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153201:20"/>of all beſides but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.)</p>
            <p>This publick ſpirit w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> they like ſo much in their Saints, they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove not ſo much in their wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men (as it ſeems) when in their 7th they urge the Amendment of the <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Adultery;</hi> &amp; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the former had gone as far as they could in <hi>Law</hi> before, to hang them up, on the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of <hi>two Witneſſes,</hi> theſe would go farther yet, and hang them up, without any <hi>Witneſſe</hi> at all; and then what a <hi>ſhower of Halters</hi> ſhould we have raining down upon our heads, when our very Sexes ſhould be our crimes, which, but with our beings, we could not depart withall?</p>
            <p>And whither with this <hi>ſeverity</hi> of theirs, would they drive this Vice at laſt, but more and more inwards ſtill? as <hi>Diogenes</hi> wittily ſaid of that Young man, who iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153201:20"/>from one of thoſe lewd places, and ſeeing him, ran in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, not to be ſeen by him, which he perceiving, call'd after him, and ſaid, That the more he ſought to hide his lewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, he but entred the further into it, and ingulphed &amp; plung'd ſelf into it the more. So we may ſay, theſe would inforce men to do, by the <hi>ſeverity</hi> of the <hi>Laws</hi> they would enact, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For (I ſpeak it not to patronage Vice, but to plead the cauſe of Virtue,) they have look'd as narrowly to this <hi>Vice</hi> already, as modeſtly they can, and to look nearer to theſe ſecret ſins, would but make them indeavor ſtill to ſin more ſecretly, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint</hi> but more irritating Vice, as we ſee in thoſe Countries where they truſt more to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint</hi> and <hi>cautel,</hi> than to peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples <hi>honeſties;</hi> it being more the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153201:21"/>
               <hi>conſcience</hi> than <hi>cautiouſneſs,</hi> can keep them honeſt; and to take off the bridle from mens <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences,</hi> and afterwards expect to conſtrain them to be <hi>virtuous,</hi> is juſt like him, who ſhould take the <hi>bridle</hi> off his Horſe, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards by <hi>ſwitching</hi> expect to manage him as he pleaſed.</p>
            <p>Beſides, the ſetting ſo high a rate on the forfeiture, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dears and renders Vice more precious; and juſt as we ſee in Gaming, makes foul play law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, by ſetting a Tax and penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty on their not playing fair; they ſeeming by that manner of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, not ſo much to puniſh the Act, as the being taken in it; whence conſequently, men ſtudy more to avoid the being taken in it, than the Act it ſelf.</p>
            <p>In the fifth, theſe lovers of Juſtice and Righteouſneſſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, to have all the burthen of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153201:21"/>Taxes and Contribution lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the <hi>Cavaliers,</hi> againſt the Publique Faith given them in their ſeveral Articles and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gteements, which <hi>Faith</hi> theſe ſeem to care as little for, as they do for <hi>Good works;</hi> whence we ſee, that had theſe men the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of Affaires, they would ſoon throw their <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Temperance</hi> after their <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> and <hi>Fortitude,</hi> hating all <hi>Cardinal virtues,</hi> ever ſince they underſtood they belonged unto the <hi>Pope;</hi> never conſidering how dearly already they have payed for their <hi>new-ſtyl'd</hi> offence, by the Sequeſtration of their whole Eſtates, or being Mulcted in the greateſt part of them, of which they are not in preſent poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but by dearly buying them again; yet would theſe moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual <hi>Juſticers</hi> have them more taxt than others who enjoy their Eſtates intire.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:153201:22"/>
            <p>And mark what a wiſe Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon they give you for it; For ſo (ſay they) <hi>It will make them the more willing to ſit stil';</hi> to <hi>riſe</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they ſhould ſay, as moſt commonly does any man of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, when he finds himſelf too much oppreſſ'd; none beſides being <hi>willing</hi> to do that, which he is forc'd unto. Theſe men who counſel and perſwade this, (like thoſe, who after a body has been once ſick, will never ſuffer it to recover health again) never conſidering, That a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth</hi> founded on the <hi>injury</hi> and <hi>oppreſsions</hi> of others, is only built for <hi>ruine</hi> and <hi>deſtruction;</hi> That <hi>ſternneſs, cruelty,</hi> and <hi>ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> is for <hi>Slaves,</hi> but for Free-born men, <hi>gentlenes</hi> &amp; <hi>debonairity;</hi> That there the Government is ever moſt aſſured, where men govern ſo, as it may be expedient for all Good men the preſent State
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:153201:22"/>ſhould continue, and thoſe who govern otherwiſe, may be ſafe, but never ſecure; and, That fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally nothing better declares the wholeſom conſtitution of a Commonwealth, than a cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and ſmiling countenance, with no diſcontent ſadding its brow: a ſad and groaning State being never long-lived, ſince as the Poet ſayes, <hi>Non vivers, ſed bene valere vita eſt,</hi> that that which we call Life, conſiſts not ſo much in living, as in living well.</p>
            <p>For which conſideration, thoſe who formerly had the ordering of the Commonwealth, after they had ſufficiently Mulcted the <hi>Cavaliers</hi> for that, which on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the fottune of the ſide ſeems to have made a <hi>crime,</hi> and an <hi>offence,</hi> wiſely admitted them by divers Treaties to Compoſition, and laſtly, by the <hi>Act of Oblivion,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:153201:23"/>to the common Freedom and Liberty with the reſt, which now to infringe, were no leſſe diſhonourable than dangerous.</p>
            <p>But in the 8th, their main Combat is againſt the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> who is alwayes the Giant theſe doughty Sir <hi>Lancelots</hi> and <hi>Don Quixots</hi> muſt overcome, and like old <hi>Calianax</hi> (in the Play) beat over and over, when any elſe hath offended them, whom they dare not meddle with. The poor <hi>Papiſt</hi> by perpetual ill uſage having been ſo cow'd and cowarded, as he lies quaking and trembling, and dares do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but pray that no body may moleſt him, he accounting it obligation to thoſe who but ſtrike him only, when they have power to kill. He is the <hi>Dogg</hi> that's always beaten in the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> preſence: and be the fault whoſe it will, he is ſure to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:153201:23"/>the blame and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſo, as if <hi>Perſecution</hi> be no the nigheſt way to <hi>Heaven,</hi> certainly he goes the fartheſt way about; Their Adverſaries (ſuch as theſe Petitioners) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways crying out againſt them, like <hi>cunning Thieves,</hi> who joyn with the <hi>Hub-bub,</hi> and follow <hi>True men</hi> with <hi>Hue</hi> and <hi>Cry,</hi> the better to eſcape themſelves. And truly I do not know why all your new <hi>ſale-made</hi> Religions (though differing among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) ſhould joyn ſo <hi>unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly,</hi> and with ſo great <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſity,</hi> againſt the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> unleſſe perhaps, for fear they ſhould marr their Market; juſt like that bungling <hi>Painter,</hi> who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving painted a <hi>Cock</hi> moſt mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrouſly ill, ſet his <hi>Boy</hi> to keep away all <hi>Cocks</hi> from about his ſhop, for fear, leſt in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with them, the deformity
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:153201:24"/>of his work ſhould more mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly appear; they advantaging the <hi>Papiſt</hi> the whilſt by making people imagine, that there is ſomwhat extraordinary in their <hi>Religion,</hi> rendring it incompati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with all other Sects; and make this <hi>dilemma,</hi> that either all <hi>Religions</hi> profeſſing <hi>Chriſt</hi> are true, or but only one; if all, why not the <hi>Papiſt</hi> amongſt the reſt? if but one, why are not the reſt as much perſecuted as he? And here I cann't omit a pleſant ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>K. James,</hi> That the <hi>Papiſt</hi> was his <hi>honeſt Aſs,</hi> on whom he might impoſe what burthen and load he pleaſed, and hee'd grunt and grunt, but patiently bear it ſtill; wheras the <hi>Puritan</hi> was like a skittiſh Jade, which kicks and winces at the leaſt load laid on him, crying out before he was hurt, to keep off danger ſtill far enough from him, which skit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhneſſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:153201:24"/>of his hath render'd him ſo reſty and pampered, as none dare hazard the breaking and backing him, but only the Army, (to whom nothing is dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult, and impoſſible) the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing of taming which wild and head-ſtrong <hi>Bucephalus,</hi> to their perpetual <hi>fame</hi> and <hi>felicity,</hi> like another <hi>Alexander,</hi> ſeeming only to be reſerv'd to them. Mean while, whoſoever out of theſe unworthy timid reſpects, does tolerate them, ſhall find, as your <hi>Kings</hi> have done, by dear Experiment at laſt, that they are in <hi>Kingdoms</hi> and <hi>Commonwealths,</hi> juſt like your <hi>Hedge-hoggs</hi> brood, which when the Damn finds prickly in her womb, ſhe ſhrinks up, and dares not inforce her ſelf to be delivered of it, till defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it from day to day, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com ſo grievous and intolerable at laſt, as they cannot be delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:153201:25"/>of them, but with their lives and all. And here comes well to purpoſe (to the <hi>Army</hi> and the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> into whoſe num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber theſe would ſo fain inſinuat themſelves) the Fable of the <hi>Hare</hi> and <hi>Hedge-hogg,</hi> who in a cold winters night came to the form or <hi>muſet</hi> of the <hi>Hare,</hi> deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to ſhelter there againſt the rigor of the ſeaſon, to whom the <hi>Hare</hi> at firſt anſwered wiſely, that her form was but ſtrait and narrow, and he ſo <hi>prickly,</hi> as without her much Incommodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhe could not admit, nor har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour him; when he craftily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, That for his <hi>prickles,</hi> as he could briſtle them up againſt an Enemy, ſo for a Friend he could couch them ſo cloſe unto his back, as they ſhould feel them no more, than as if they were <hi>down</hi> or <hi>feathers;</hi> which the <hi>Hare</hi> ſimply believing, admitted him
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:153201:25"/>into her form, where he was no ſooner come, but he began to briſtle, &amp; ſo gor'd the poor <hi>Hare,</hi> as ſhe cried out for pain, when the <hi>Hedge-hogg</hi> gave it only this comfort and anſwer, for all its hoſpitality, <hi>That thoſe who found themſelves agrieved, might quit the place;</hi> and here I leave to each one the Application, to come to the examining what grievous crime they charge the <hi>Papiſt</hi> with, as 'tis moſt commonly no leſs than the Invaſion of the Land, or the blowing up the <hi>Thames,</hi> &amp;c. to the deſtruction both of fiſh and fleſh.</p>
            <p>For that <hi>Papiſts,</hi> &amp;c. (ſay they) <hi>take liberty of contemning the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, and publique Ordinances, and ſpend the day vainly and idlely in their houſes, or elſe walking in the fields,</hi> we propoſe <hi>That ſome ſpecial courſe may be taken of reſtraint, &amp;c.</hi> And what unreaſonable people
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:153201:26"/>are theſe, that will not permit them to go to Church, nor tarry at home, to remain in their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, nor to walk abroad in the fields? what they would have of them elſe, I do not know, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they would inforce them to work on the <hi>Sabbath day;</hi> &amp; more unreaſonable would they be yet, to ſeek to enforce them to go to other Churches beſides their own. If they think they be ſo idle at home, why do they ſearch their houſes ſo oft to find them at <hi>Maſs?</hi> and what reſtraint they intend, I do not ſee, unleſſe they mean to <hi>pound</hi> them, when they catch them in the fields. In fine, their condition is lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the whilſt they will not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them the liberty of their own houſes, nor ſo much as the benefit of common air: But of this enough.</p>
            <p>The next whom they fall foul
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:153201:26"/>upon (in the 6th) are your <hi>Wakes</hi> and <hi>Moris-dances,</hi> meaning quite to overthrow the <hi>Hobby-horſe,</hi> horſe and man, holding him lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le better than the <hi>beaſt,</hi> and <hi>maid Marian</hi> the <hi>whore</hi> of <hi>Babylon.</hi> Mean time, what harm the poor <hi>Moris-dancers</hi> do unto them, I do not ſee, but only that the <hi>melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly</hi> Devil which poſſeſſes them is enemy of all mirth and harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Recreation, which makes the poor ſouls in ſighing, wiſh for the <hi>merry devil of Edmonton</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and the days of <hi>Puck,</hi> and <hi>Robin-goodfellow,</hi> as I doubt not but their wiſdoms who govern the Commonwealth wil ſhortly grant them u'm, &amp; reſtore them their former ſports again, which as they during the Time of our late Calamities did prudently debar them of, (when, indeed, all mirth had been unſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) ſo that time once over, they
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:153201:27"/>will ſuffer them, no doubt, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn unto them again, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that as the Poet ſaid, <hi>Pane &amp; Circenſe,</hi> give them but ſports and bread enough, and you may rule them at pleaſure: whereas, take from them but thoſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>amuſements</hi> of their minds, and you but convert their thoughts inwards, to meditate on nothing but their grievances, and diſcontent; for which Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, perhaps theſe men would prohibit, and abridge them of them, that ſo they might only ſtudy miſchief, like themſelves. Mean time, ſuch as theſe would make rare Governors of the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth,</hi> who, whilſt they ſhould be making <hi>Acts,</hi> for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercoming of our Enemies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, and rendring us formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to all the world, would be making <hi>Acts</hi> againſt <hi>Moris-dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers,</hi> and <hi>Hobby-horſes,</hi> to render
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:153201:27"/>us ridiculous unto every one.</p>
            <p>And thus much may ſuffice to ſhew the malice and foppery of their Petition, which I know wil fret and vex them to the very hearts (&amp; much good do't their good hearts with it) to ſee the ſecrets of their <hi>Cabal</hi> diſcovered, and their deſigns laid open, ſo pernicious to the preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the <hi>Commonwealth;</hi> It being the <hi>Religion</hi> of the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon fry,</hi> and ſuch brown-bread ſpirits of the ſame batch with them, they making the <hi>Rabble</hi> their only <hi>Rabbins,</hi> and inviting them to <hi>liberty,</hi> which in effect is nothing elſe, but <hi>licentiouſnes,</hi> and <hi>Shrovetide-Ryot,</hi> ſuch having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to loſe, being ſure to gain by each change and mutation: The more deſerving the <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates</hi> care and <hi>coertion,</hi> the more numerous, and indigent they ar. Mean time, 't ſhall never repent
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:153201:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>me to be an <hi>Enemy</hi> of thoſe are Enemies to my Country and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and I'm ſure the <hi>Army</hi> &amp; <hi>Republique</hi> will thank me for't, theſe men being the greateſt Enemies they have, as their many vain Attempts to change the Government of the one, and fight againſt the other, ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently declare. To conclude, all men are to admire the rare tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and wiſdom of the State to admit of all Petitions, and yet be moved with none but ſuch as may be ſalutarie for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, and rejoice in the Liberty the people of <hi>England</hi> enjoy, the while they can deliver ſuch Petitions as theſe, without being ſent to <hi>Bedlam</hi> for their pains.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
